Susy **Echeverria-Londono, Ph.D.**

DATA SCIENTIST AND RESEARCHER

CONTACT DETAILS

- @ susyelo@gmail.com
- +33 6 36 01 15 45
- susyelo.github.io
- ⋈ Paris area, France

PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Multidisciplinary researcher with 10+ years experience at the intersection of biodiversity, public health, and environmental science. Expert in synthesising and communicating complex research findings to scientists, policymakers, and broader audiences. Strong skills in scientific synthesis, data visualisation, and collaborative leadership across Europe, the Americas, and international consortia (e.g., WHO, GAVI, NSF, VIMC).

RELEVANT SKILLS

- Tools: R, Python, SQL, statistical analysis, Git, LaTeX, Shiny and Power BI dashboards.
- Experience collaborating with cross-functional teams (including policy analysts, domain experts, and software developers) to design analytical solutions aligned with strategic goals.
- Experience in delivering presentations and writing reports to diverse audiences, including scientists, policymakers, and non-technical audiences.
- Great ability to synthesise complex data into accessible insights.
- Proactive and well-organised, with strong prioritisation skills and a collaborative team spirit.
- Multilingual: native in Spanish, professional competence in English, and intermediate level in French and Italian.

INTERESTS

Outside of work, I am very interested in all types of dancing. I enjoy countryside trips with my dog and family, and in the future I would love volunteering at dog shelters.

EXPERIENCE

RESEARCH CONSULTANT (FREELANCE) Global/Remote

2022- now

- Supported policy-making institutions in assessing the potential for harmonizing and integrating vaccine impact estimates across platforms.
- Communicated findings through reports with global-health stakeholders (VIMC, GAVI and BMGF).

RESEARCH CONSULTANT AND RESEARCH ASSOCIATE Imperial College London, UK

2019-2022

- Analysed, organised, and prepared time series vaccine impact estimates for 12 pathogens across 112 countries from 21 models developed by institutions worldwide.
- Ensured robust and policy-relevant outputs for decision making in global health and produced regular technical reports to inform stakeholders and support evidence-based vaccine investment and advocacy.
- Delivered and organised webinars to discuss data-driven results to domain experts and stakeholders. PI: Prof. Neil M. Ferguson; Line manager: Dr Katy Gaythorpe.

NSF POSTDOCTORAL ASSOCIATE Kenyon College, Ohio, USA

2017-2019

- Demonstrated advanced skills in spatial data analysis and handling of large ecological datasets by conducting in-depth quantitative analysis of functional diversity among plant species across North and South American biomes.
- Co-developed and taught the course "Global Ecology and Biogeography" focused on quantitative ecological analyses using R.
- Performed spatial data analysis on 300 plant species using spatial point pattern analysis.
- Analysed datasets comprising 85,000 plant species and over 9 million georeferenced data points. Pls: Prof. Andrew Kerkhoff and Prof. Brian J. Enquist.

LECTURER AND DEMONSTRATOR

2013-2017

Natural History Museum and Imperial College London, UK

- Coordinated field-based data collection and analysis between Colombian researchers and UK institutions.
- Contributed to high-level scientific diplomacy, presenting biodiversity findings to political leaders including the Colombian president, ministers and Prince Charles.

EDUCATION

Рн.D. in Life Science.

Imperial College London, UK

2013-2017

⋄ Thesis: Plant macroevolution and biodiversity responses to land-use change.

M.RES. in Biodiversity, Informatics and Genomics (with distinction)

Imperial College London, UK

20

2012-2013

♦ Thesis: Effects of land use on local biodiversity in Colombia.

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE in Biology (with 1st-class honours)
Universidad Industrial de Santander, Colombia

2004-2010

SELECTED PROJECTS & ACCOMPLISHMENTS

- Managed the regular delivery of high-level reports to stakeholders (WHO, GAVI, BMGF), meeting strict deadlines.
- Managed data acquisition and international communication for biodiversity monitoring initiatives between Colombian and European researchers ensuring bilateral cooperation (e.g., the PREDICTS).
- 30+ peer-reviewed articles in Lancet, Nature, eLife, and Vaccine (cf. https://susyelo.github.io/publications.html).
- Awarded "Outstanding Paper by Young Investigator" (JSE, 2022).